Hi, welcome back to the meditations for
this middle of the sun lam rim retreat.
And we've reached the fourth meditation
which you will be doing during the
fourth week. You'll be doing it during
episodes 10 to 12 if I'm correct right?
And... so you'll be doing it that week that
you're studying episodes 10 to 12. And we
are continuing with the chapter--the
tenth chapter, from Master Shantideva--
which is called the chapter on
dedication. BSNGO BA'I LE'U. And we are
in the fourth section of that
meditation. Now, don't forget what Master
Shantideva is doing with that section--
he's dedicating a good karma. What good
karma?
Of finishing the book okay?
So the
tenth chapter is the dedication of the
writing the first nine chapters. It's
kind of cool. So he's done this good
karma.... he's got this big pile of good
karma. You know, sometimes you get a
unexpected profit from your business you
know? It happens. It happens to me from
time to time, and I suddenly I get this
big amount of money and then
and then you have to think of how you're
going to give it away. So you can
feel that with Master Shantideva here.
He's like got this big good
karma landed in his hands of writing the
Guide to the Bodhisattvas Way of Life--
and now he's going to have to... he wants to
give it away because he wants to protect
it. So he wants to give that good karma
to other people.
So we're in the fourth
part of that, and you and me we're going to
try to emulate Shantideva. We're going to
think of some good karma we did--and
this lam rim says
that a small good
deed during a difficult time in the
world
is a big good deed.
Maybe as
big as what Shantideva did you see?
So normally if there was no virus, being
nice to your neighbor wouldn't be such a
big thing but in the time of the virus
to be sweet to your neighbor, to help
your neighbor, that becomes a very
powerful good karma.
It's so powerful
that we can do an act of truth okay?
Act of truth is: we say to ourselves... in
our meditation we're going to say, if it's
true that I got to know the neighbor at
the end of my street... okay I'll tell you
secretly he was a Marine colonel
and he was a fundamentalist Christian
preacher together okay? And then we
never talked to each other before... he's
old now. But we got to such a sweet
relationship now, we worked on it... we both
worked on it. We didn't start out with a
very good relationship, but we worked on
it and the virus helped us. So I'm going to
dedicate this karma you know? That's the
good deed I did during the virus.
We became quite close friends and I'm very
proud of that--that's my lam rim practice
for for the last few months.
And I worked
on it and he worked on it I'm sure.
So that's the good karma and then I'm going to
dedicate it. I'm going to use it. For what?
"If it's true that I became close friends
with my neighbor... that we didn't like
each other before the virus... then should
the virus itself be sent to the middle
of the sun and burnt up for everybody!"
25 million degrees okay?
"By this act
of truth which could turn Niagara Falls
backwards...
I dedicate that act of truth to
shooting the virus into the middle of
sun for people on this planet." Okay so
here we go.
Get ready for your meditation.
Small smile.
Relax forehead.
Tummies in. Virus...
Covid tummy's pulled in a little bit.
Hands are comfortable... chin mudra if you like.
Back is straight. Shoulders are back.
And let's prepare by taking ten breaths.
Ten long exhales, that's all.
Very slow. Very long.
So for this meditation, we're going to do an
act of truth.
For an act of truth you
need some ammunition--you need a good
deed that you have done.
Particularly in
the last few months during this world
crisis... world problem.
And so let's each
one of us think about some special
thing that we did that was kind or nice
to someone else during the virus. We all
did something.
That's going to be our
ammunition.
Let's think about that.
Something nice you did during the virus
time. Just one is enough.
Make it clear.
Now let's dedicate that. Let's do an act
of truth.
If it's true that I did this
kindness during the virus then... and
here's a list from Shantideva.
Then may there be beautiful gardens.
Lovely gardens appear in this world.
And people sitting in those gardens and enjoying
learning goodness.
Dharma... learning the Dharma.
Doesn't have to be Buddhist Dharma but
may there come to be beautiful places...
maybe this is where we'll have to go
back to teaching Dharma in large
gardens as in the Buddha's time with
social distancing in the garden. And may
their appear gardens in this world.
And people relaxing on the grass or on a
bench
speaking about lam rim.
if it's true that I was good during the
virus
may there be teachings for everyone. May
everyone meet the teacher who fits them.
Through my good deed
may everyone meet the teacher who fits them.
Now Shantideva makes a very interesting
prayer. May the economy of the world be
healthy.
May the governments be well-managed
governments that serve their peoples
well.
And of course, may the weather be good
and may the crops be successful and
plentiful.
May we have good governance
around the world. May we have good
economy--world economy.
If I was nice during the virus.
Shantideva next prayer is very
interesting.
If it's true that I was good
during the virus to someone then may
medicines in this world be effective.
May medicines work for people. May the
vaccine against this virus be found
quickly and may it work for everybody.
Very interesting prayer that Shantideva
made over a thousand years ago for us.
May no one feel pain or fear.
May no one
be unhappy.
May no one be hurt by another
person.
Where people are studying spiritual practice,
whatever religion it may be,
may
they be successful
and may there be
harmony in that group. And may they do
good practice together. May all churches,
mosques, temples, or even people who have
no religion, may they live in harmony.
May their wisdom increase by my act of truth.
May people believe in higher things.
May
they learn to make offerings to
higher beings that they cannot see.
May they always be reborn as a human and
may they reach enlightenment.
Then there are plenty of Buddhas in the
Universe. There are countless bodhisattvas in
the universe.
And Shantideva makes an interesting prayer--act of truth.
Those Buddhas and bodhisattvas they have
plans for us. For you, for me, for our
family, for our friends, for our country.
They have plans for us. They have
plans in mind for us. And they may even
involve going on a lower path for a
while--but I dedicate the good karma of
the service I gave to others during the
virus that those plans should come true.
They should succeed in the plans they
have for me and for you. Those plans
should succeed.
May all beings see emptiness in this
universe.
May all beings practice loving
each other mainly.
May they learn to do
deep retreat.
May places like Diamond Mountain
grow in many parts of this
world where people can go and do deep retreat.
We're doing sort of a retreat
during the virus, but it's good to get
out of your own home and go to a special
place where people just do retreat.
And the buildings are built for retreat. May
those retreat centers thrive, and be
healthy, and serve many people. If I have
been nice to someone during the virus...
try to remember the good thing you did.
Send strong prayers to spiritual
communities of all religions.
Pray for their success.
Please come back to your breath. Three
long exhales.
Then slowly open your eyes. Take a
stretch. Yay!
Nice job.
See you in the next meditation.